paylution.com 2010-02-03

# Paylution prepaid debit card product and service privacy policy

When you become a PAYlution cardholder, and in the course of your transactions through PAYlution, you share some of your important personal information with us. Your privacy is important to us and we understand the sensitive nature of this information. PAYlution is vigilant in its efforts to ensure that information about its cardholders is protected. While your privacy has always been important to us, our new Privacy Policy provides you with all of the safeguards set forth in the Canadian federal Personal Information Protection and Electronic Documents Act (PIPEDA) and in other applicable personal information protection legislation ("Privacy Laws"). Nothing in this Privacy Policy will limit our rights and obligations pursuant to such Privacy Laws. 

* * *

**  
CONSENT  
**BY SUBMITTING PERSONAL INFORMATION TO PAYlution OR ITS SERVICE PROVIDERS AND AGENTS, YOU AGREE THAT PAYlution AND ITS SERVICE PROVIDERS AND AGENTS MAY COLLECT, USE AND DISCLOSE SUCH PERSONAL INFORMATION IN ACCORDANCE WITH THIS PRIVACY POLICY AND AS PERMITTED OR REQUIRED BY PRIVACY LAWS. 

Subject to legal and contractual requirements, you may refuse or withdraw your consent to certain of the identified purposes at any time by contacting the PAYlution Privacy Officer. If you refuse or withdraw your consent, we may not be able to provide you or continue to provide you with certain services or information which may be of value to you. If you provide PAYlution or its service providers and agents with personal information of another individual, you represent that you have all necessary authority and/or have obtained all necessary consents from such person to enable us to collect, use and disclose such personal information for the purposes set forth in this Privacy Policy. 

**  
WHAT PERSONAL INFORMATION DO WE COLLECT?**  
Personal information means any information about you except your business title, address, e-mail address, telephone number or facsimile number. 

The types of personal information that PAYlution may collect from you from time to time include: your name, home address, telephone number, personal e-mail address, your forwarding address (e.g. during a vacation), previous address(es), billing and account information (such as credit card, or bank account number), your mailing preferences, delivery instructions, and customer service preferences. In addition, from time to time, we may ask you to provide us with more detailed information regarding your interests, occupation and background. For example, we sometimes ask our customers to complete surveys in order to get a better sense of who they are and what issues, products or services may be of interest to our clients. 

* * *

**  
PAYlution's PRIVACY PRINCIPALS**

PAYlution collects, uses and discloses your personal information by employing "fair information practices" as described in the following privacy principles and embodied in Privacy Laws: 

  1. **ACCOUNTABILITY:**  
Accountability for PAYlution's compliance with this Privacy Policy rests with PAYlution's Privacy Officer. The Privacy Officer may delegate other individuals to act in his or her behalf. PAYlution is responsible for all personal information under its control. All PAYlution employees have been advised of their responsibilities under the Personal Information Protection and Electronic Documents Act (Canada) and the Personal Information Protection Act (British Columbia), but the overall responsibility for the protection of personal information and compliance with this policy rests with PAYlution's Privacy Officer. PAYlution is committed to ensuring that the appropriate security measures are employed in the storage or transfer of sensitive information. However, in relation to e-mail or wireless communication, complete confidentiality and security cannot be assured. Remember that e-mail sent over the Internet is generally unencrypted. We recommend that you use caution when contacting us via e-mail and that you do not include confidential information (such as financial institution account numbers) in those messages, as they are not encrypted. 

PAYlution is not accountable for any damages suffered when a cardholder transmits personal information through e-mail or wireless communication to PAYlution or when PAYlution transmits personal information via e-mail or wireless communication to a client on request.

  2. **IDENTIFYING PURPOSES:**  
The purposes for which personal information is collected shall be identified by PAYlution before or at the time the information is collected. There are certain specific reasons why PAYlution needs to collect your personal information: 

>     * to establish your identity and obtain contact information for you; 
>     * to maintain and provide card services; 
>     * to process transactions; 
>     * to protect you and us from error and fraud; 
>     * to develop and mange our business and operations; 
>     * to distribute our news letters and other material to individuals on our mail and e-mail lists, including via third party mailing houses and e-mail service providers; 
>     * to understand and respond to your needs and preferences, including to contact and communicate with you and to conduct surveys, research and evaluations; 
>     * to develop, enhance, market, sell or otherwise provide our products and services; 
>     * as permitted by, and to comply with, any legal or regulatory requirements or provisions; and for any purpose to which you consent. 

To ensure the accuracy of your instructions and to monitor the quality of service, PAYlution may record its telephone calls. If you have concerns about the recording of your telephone conversations, you should contact us by e-mail or by regular mail. PAYlution collects, uses, and discloses personal information only for purposes that are directly related to the processing of transactions, and that a reasonable person would consider appropriate under those circumstances.

  3. **CONSENT:**  
**The knowledge and consent of the individual are required for the collection, use or disclosure of personal information, except as provided by law.**

Your knowledge and consent are required before we may collect, use or release your personal information to anyone outside of PAYlution, except in special circumstances. These special circumstances include times when your consent is deemed given by law or not required by law. These circumstances may include, but are not limited to, a fraud investigation, an investigation by police, or where the financial institution from which you transferred funds to PAYlution is unable to contact you. PAYlution may be compelled to release your information by a court of law, or by another legal authority, regulatory authority (including self regulatory authority), or governmental body. In all cases, our policy is to release information only to the extent that we are required to do so. 

**Your consent can be express or implied:**  
By entering your personal information on PAYlution's website, you are implicitly consenting to the collection of that information. PAYlution will seek your express consent before disclosing your information for purposes other than those specified in this Policy or that a reasonable person would expect, unless such a request would compromise an investigation. 

**You can withdraw your consent after you have given it:**  
An individual may withdraw consent at any time, subject to legal or contractual restrictions and reasonable notice. To withdraw your consent you must contact our Privacy Officer, in writing, using the contact information listed in this Policy. If you do not consent to certain uses of information, or if you withdraw your consent, PAYlution may not be able to provide you with a particular product or service or we may not be able to provide service to you at all.

  4. **LIMITING COLLECTION:**  
The collection of personal information shall be limited to that which is necessary for the purposes identified by PAYlution. The information shall be collected by fair and lawful means. Personal information shall not be collected indiscriminately. Both the amount and the type of information collected shall be limited to that which is necessary to fulfill the purposes identified. 
  5. **LIMITING USE, DISCLOSURE, AND RETENTION:**  
Personal information shall not be used or disclosed for purposes other than those for which the information was collected, except with the consent of the individual or as required by law. Personal information shall be retained only as long as necessary for the fulfillment of those purposes. 

**The information is only used for specific purposes:**  
Personal information will only be used or disclosed for the purpose(s) for which it is collected. PAYlution will not use personal information for any additional purpose unless we obtain your consent to do so. 

PAYlution will not sell personal information to any third party. However, it may be necessary for PAYlution to disclose your information to the following third parties: 

>     * Your employer (including authorized staff); 
>     * PAYlution (including those with whom PAYlution has contracted to provide Card related services; 
>     * third party operators to whom Alterna Bank has outsourced the management of Card issuing and Cardholder inquiries; 
>     * legal, financial, and professional advisors; and 
>     * governmental agencies. 

**Your information is destroyed when it is no longer needed:**  
PAYlution keeps your information only for as long as we need it. Please note that PAYlution retains your information for a period of five (5) years after the completion of our services to you in order to assist you and in reviewing your historical account information when necessary and to enable us to provide more comprehensive security. 

  6. **ACCURACY:**  
Personal information shall be as accurate, complete and up-to-date as is necessary for the purposes for which it is used. PAYlution will make reasonable efforts to ensure that personal information is as accurate, complete and current as required for the purposes for which it was collected. In many cases, PAYlution relies on its cardholders to ensure that certain information, such as their address or telephone number, is current, complete and accurate. You can check your information to verify, update and correct it, and to have any obsolete information removed. Please make your request in writing to our Privacy Officer as set out in this Policy. PAYlution will charge a reasonable fee for accessing your information. 
  7. **SAFEGUARDS:**  
Security safeguards appropriate to the sensitivity of the information shall protect personal information. Security safeguards shall protect personal information against loss or theft, as well as unauthorized access, disclosure, copying, use or modification. The safeguards may include, for example, the physical security of offices and storage facilities or electronic security measures such as passwords, encryption, firewalls, and secure connections. PAYlution is not accountable for any damages suffered when a customer transmits personal information through e-mail to PAYlution or when PAYlution transmits personal information via e-mail in response to a request from the cardholder. Care shall be used in the disposal or destruction of personal information to prevent unauthorized parties from gaining access to the information. 
  8. **OPENNESS:**  
PAYlution is open about the policies and procedures it uses to protect personal information. Information about those policies and procedures will be made available either electronically or in written format in plain language. However, to ensure the integrity of our security procedures and business methods, PAYlution may refuse to publicly disclose certain information. 

PAYlution will make the following information available: 

>     * The title, e-mail address, and mailing address of the Privacy Officer, and how an individual may contact the Privacy Officer with respect to complaints or inquiries 
>     * A description of the type of personal information held by PAYlution including a general explanation of its use 
>     * Information on how an individual can gain access to the personal information held by PAYlution by contacting the Privacy Officer, confirming their identity, and requesting specified information 
>     * An explanation of what personal information is made available to related organizations 

  9. **INDIVIDUAL ACCESS:**  
You have the right to access the personal information held by PAYlution. Please make any requests for access in writing, stating as specifically as possible the personal information you are requesting. Upon request, PAYlution will, within a reasonable time period, tell you what personal information it has, what it is being used for, and to whom it has been disclosed, if applicable. Before providing any information to the requestor, PAYlution must verify the individual's identity. PAYlution may also refuse to provide access where it would reveal personal information about, or the identity of, a third party that cannot be severed from the information about the individual making the request, and in certain other circumstances there needs to be notification of governmental institutions before release. Access may also be refused where the information is protected by solicitor-client privilege; where revealing the information would also reveal information confidential to PAYlution; where revealing the information could reasonably be expected to threaten the life, health or security of an individual; if the information was collected during an investigation of a breach of an agreement or a contravention of the laws of Canada or a province on the expectation that the knowledge or consent of the individual would compromise the availability or accuracy of the information; where the information was generated in the course of a formal dispute resolution process; or where access may otherwise be prohibited or limited at law. In such cases, PAYlution will explain the reasons it will not provide the requested information. 

**  
We will respond to your request promptly:**   
PAYlution will deal quickly with your request for access, usually responding to your request within 30 days. If we need to extend the time, or we must refuse your request, we will tell you why, subject to any legal restrictions and we will notify you of the new deadline, the reasons for the extension, and of your right to make a complaint to the relevant privacy commissioner regarding the extension. 

When an individual successfully demonstrates the inaccuracy or incompleteness of personal information, PAYlution must amend the information as required. Depending upon the nature of the information challenged, amendment could involve the correction, deletion or addition of information. Where appropriate, the amended information shall be transmitted to third parties having access to the information in question. 

When a challenge is not resolved to the satisfaction of the customer, the substance of the unresolved challenge shall be recorded by PAYlution. When appropriate, the existence of the unresolved challenge shall be transmitted to third parties having access to the information in question. 

PAYlution will charge you a reasonable fee for providing access to your personal information.

  10. **COMPLIANCE, COMPLAINTS AND CONTACT INFORMATION:**  
An individual shall be able to address a challenge concerning compliance with the above privacy principles to the Privacy Officer. If you have any questions or complaints about our privacy policies, or about how PAYlution is living up to them, let us know right away. 

PAYlution is committed to treating you with the greatest respect and consideration, and providing the highest level of service. Even so, from time to time something may go wrong. There may be a misunderstanding, or you may feel you have been dealt with unjustly. In most cases, bringing this matter to our attention will resolve a complaint. Whatever the circumstances, resolving the problem for you is our primary concern. 

Please contact our Privacy Officer to discuss any privacy issues or concerns you might have, or to lodge a complaint. Our Privacy Officer can be contacted in the following ways: 

**  
By Mail:**  
Privacy Officer  
hyperWALLET Systems Inc.  
Suite 1200, 736 Granville St.  
Vancouver, BC V6Z 1G3 

**By E-mail:**  

Should you not be able to accept PAYlution's conclusion of your complaint, or at any time in the complaint process, you may also write to the relevant provincial Privacy Commissioner, or if applicable, the Privacy Commissioner of Canada. We have a separate Privacy Policy For Employees, which contains certain additional provisions. 

* * *

**  
CHANGES TO OUR PRIVACY POLICY**  
From time to time PAYlution may make changes to this policy to adapt to changing business conditions and for other reasons. In the event that changes are made to the Privacy Policy, the amended Privacy Policy will be posted on our website, along with a notice indicating that it has been changed. Cardholders will have the opportunity to withdraw their consent to the collection, use and/or disclosure of their personal information. 

**

PRIVACY AND OUR WEBSITE

**   

**Cookies:** When you access our website, we may use a browser feature called a "cookie" to collect information, such as the type of Internet browser and operating system you use, the domain name of the website from which you came, date and duration of the visit, number of visits, average time spent on our website, pages viewed and number of cookies accumulated. A cookie is a small text file containing a unique identification number that identifies your browser, but not necessarily you, to our computers each time our website is visited. Unless you specifically inform us (e.g. by registering for an event or sending us correspondence from the website), we will not know who you are. In addition to the identified purposes described in our Privacy Policy, we may use this website information and share it with other organizations with whom we have a commercial relationship to measure the use of our website, to improve the functionality and content of the website and to facilitate usage by you. You can reset your browser either to notify you when you have received a cookie or refuse to accept cookies. However, if you refuse to accept cookies, you may not be able to use some of the features available on our website. 

**Online Communications:** In order to provide you with products, services or information, you may voluntarily submit personal information to us through our website for purposes such as conducting business online, asking a question, obtaining information, reviewing or downloading a publication, participating in an event, and participating in contests and surveys. If you are known to PAYlution as a registered user of an online service, we may combine and store personal information about your use of our website and the online information you have provided with certain other online and offline information we may have collected. All collection, use and disclosure of personal information obtained through our website shall be subject to this Privacy Policy and Privacy Laws. 

**E-mail Communications:** Occasionally, we may send marketing or promotional e-mail communications to you with information that may be useful, including information about the services of PAYlution and other third parties with whom we have a relationship. We will include instructions on how to unsubscribe and inform us of preferences if you decide you do not want to receive any future marketing or promotional e-mails from PAYlution. 

**Links:** Our website may contain links to other websites which are provided as a convenience only. Visitors are advised that other third party websites may have different privacy policies and practices than PAYlution, and PAYlution has no responsibility for such third party websites.
